<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="gemfire-bootstrap" version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
	<title>Bootstrapping a Spring ApplicationContext in GemFire</title>

	<section>
		<title id="gemfire-bootstrap:intro">Introduction</title>

		<para>
			Normally, a Spring-based application will <link linkend="bootstrap">bootstrap GemFire</link> using
			Spring Data GemFire's XML namespace. Just by specifying a <literal>&lt;gfe:cache/&gt;</literal> element
			in Spring Data GemFire configuration meta-data, a single, peer GemFire Cache instance will be created
			and initialized with default settings in the same JVM process as your application.
		</para>

		<para>
			However, sometimes it is a requirement, perhaps imposed by your IT operations team, that GemFire must be
			fully managed and operated using the provided GemFire tool suite, such as with
			<ulink url="http://pubs.vmware.com/vfabric53/topic/com.vmware.vfabric.gemfire.7.0/tools_modules/gfsh/chapter_overview.html">Gfsh</ulink>.
			Using <emphasis>Gfsh</emphasis>, even though the application and GemFire will share the same JVM process,
			GemFire will bootstrap your Spring application context rather than the other way around. So, using this
			approach GemFire, instead of an application server, or a Java main class using Spring Boot, will bootstrap
			and host your application.
		</para>

		<para>
			Keep in mind, however, that GemFire is not an application server.  In addition, there are limitations
			to using this approach where GemFire Cache configuration is concerned.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title id="gemfire-bootstrap:initializer">Using GemFire to Bootstrap a Spring Context Started with Gfsh</title>

		<para>
			In order to bootstrap a Spring application context in GemFire when starting a GemFire Server process
			using Gfsh, a user must make use of GemFire's
			<ulink url="http://pubs.vmware.com/vfabric53/topic/com.vmware.vfabric.gemfire.7.0/basic_config/the_cache/setting_cache_initializer.html">Initalizer</ulink>
			functionality.  An <emphasis>Initializer</emphasis> can be used to specify a callback application that
			is launched after the Cache is initialized by GemFire.
		</para>

		<para>
			An <emphasis>Initializer</emphasis> is specified within an
			<ulink url="http://pubs.vmware.com/vfabric53/topic/com.vmware.vfabric.gemfire.7.0/reference/topics/cache_xml.html?path=4_1_9_1_2_21#initializer">initializer</ulink>
			element using a minimal snippet of GemFire's native configuration meta-data inside
			a <literal>cache.xml</literal> file. The <literal>cache.xml</literal> file is required in order to
			bootstrap the Spring application context, much like a minimal snippet of Spring XML config is needed to
			bootstrap a Spring application context configured with component scanning
			(e.g. <literal>&lt;context:component-scan base-packages="..."/&gt;</literal>)
		</para>

		<para>
			As of Spring Data GemFire 1.4, such an <emphasis>Initializer</emphasis> is already conveniently provided
			by the framework, the <classname>org.springframework.data.gemfire.support.SpringContextBootstrappingInitializer</classname>.
			The typical, yet minimal configuration for this class inside GemFire's <literal>cache.xml</literal> file
			will look like the following:
		</para>

		<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE cache PUBLIC  "-//GemStone Systems, Inc.//GemFire Declarative Caching 7.0//EN"
  "http://www.gemstone.com/dtd/cache7_0.dtd">

<cache>
  <initializer>
    <class-name>org.springframework.data.gemfire.support.SpringContextBootstrappingInitializer</class-name>
    <parameter name="contextConfigLocations">
      <string>classpath:application-context.xml</string>
    </parameter>
  </initializer>
</cache>]]>
		</programlisting>

		<para>
			The <classname>SpringContextBootstrappingInitializer</classname> class follows similar conventions as
			Spring's ContextLoaderListener class for bootstrapping a Spring context inside a Web Application, where
			application context configuration files are specified with the <literal>contextConfigLocations</literal>
			Servlet Context Parameter.  In addition, the <classname>SpringContextBootstrappingInitializer</classname>
			class can also be used with a <literal>basePackages</literal> parameter to specify a comma-separated list
			of base package containing the appropriately annotated application components that the Spring container
			will search using component scanning and create Spring beans for:
		</para>

		<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE cache PUBLIC  "-//GemStone Systems, Inc.//GemFire Declarative Caching 7.0//EN"
  "http://www.gemstone.com/dtd/cache7_0.dtd">

<cache>
  <initializer>
    <class-name>org.springframework.data.gemfire.support.SpringContextBootstrappingInitializer</class-name>
    <parameter name="basePackages">
      <string>org.mycompany.myapp.services,org.mycompany.myapp.dao,...</string>
    </parameter>
  </initializer>
</cache>]]>
		</programlisting>

		<para>
			Then, with a properly configured and constructed <literal>CLASSPATH</literal> along with the
			<literal>cache.xml</literal> file shown above specified as a command-line option when starting
			a GemFire Server in Gfsh, the command-line would be:
		</para>

		<programlisting>gfsh>start server --name=Server1 --log-level=config ...
			--classpath="/path/to/spring-data-gemfire-1.4.0.jar:/path/to/application/classes.jar"
			--cache-xml-file="/path/to/gemfire/cache.xml"
		</programlisting>

		<para>
			The <literal>application-context.xml</literal> can be any valid Spring context configuration meta-data
			including all the SDG namespace elements. The only limitation with this approach is that the GemFire
			Cache cannot be configured using the Spring Data GemFire namespace.  In other words, none of the
			<literal>&lt;gfe:cache/&gt;</literal> element attributes, such as <literal>cache-xml-location</literal>,
			<literal>properties-ref</literal>, <literal>critical-heap-percentage</literal>, <literal>pdx-serializer-ref</literal>,
			<literal>lock-lease</literal>, etc can be specified. If used, these attributes will be ignored.
			The main reason for this is that GemFire itself has already created an initialized the Cache before
			the <emphasis>Initializer</emphasis> gets invoked. As such, the Cache will already exist and since it is
			a "Singleton", it cannot be re-initialized or have any of it's configuration augmented.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title id="gemfire-bootstrap:lazy-wiring">Lazy-Wiring GemFire Components</title>

		<para>
			Spring Data GemFire already provides existing support for wiring GemFire components (such as CacheListeners,
			CacheLoaders or CacheWriters) that are declared and created by GemFire in <literal>cache.xml</literal>
			using the <classname>WiringDeclarableSupport</classname> class as described in
			<xref linkend="apis:declarable:autowiring"/>.
			However, this only works when Spring does the bootstrapping (i.e. bootstraps GemFire). When your Spring
			application context is the one bootstrapped by GemFire, then these GemFire components go unnoticed since
			the Spring application context does not even exist yet!  The Spring application context will not get created
			until GemFire calls the <emphasis>Initializer</emphasis>, which occurs after all the other GemFire components
			and configuration have already been created and initialized.
		</para>

		<para>
			So, in order to solve this problem, a new <classname>LazyWiringDeclarableSupport</classname> class was
			introduced, that is, in a sense, Spring application context aware.  The intention of this abstract
			base class is that any implementing class will register itself to be configured by the Spring
			application context created by GemFire after the <emphasis>Initializer</emphasis> is called.  In essence,
			this give your GemFire managed component a chance to be configured and auto-wired with Spring beans defined
			in the Spring application context.
		</para>

		<para>
			In order for your GemFire application component to be auto-wired by the Spring container, create a
			application class that extends the <classname>LazyWiringDeclarableSupport</classname> and annotate
			any class member that needs to be provided as a Spring bean dependency, similar to:
		</para>

		<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[
public static final class UserDataSourceCacheLoader extends LazyWiringDeclarableSupport implements CacheLoader<String, User> {

  @Autowired
  private DataSource userDataSource;

  ...
}
		]]></programlisting>

		<para>
			As implied by the CacheLoader example above, you might necessarily (although, rare) have defined both
			a Region and CacheListener component in GemFire <literal>cache.xml</literal>.  The CacheLoader may need
			access to an application DAO, or perhaps Spring application context defined JDBC Data Source
			for loading "Users" into a GemFire Cache <literal>REPLICATE</literal> Region on start.  Of course,
			one should be careful in mixing the different life-cycles of GemFire and the Spring Container together
			in this manner as not all use cases and scenarios are supported.  The GemFire <literal>cache.xml</literal>
			configuration would be similar to the following (which comes from SDG's test suite):
		</para>

		<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE cache PUBLIC  "-//GemStone Systems, Inc.//GemFire Declarative Caching 7.0//EN"
  "http://www.gemstone.com/dtd/cache7_0.dtd">

<cache>
  <region name="Users" refid="REPLICATE">
    <region-attributes initial-capacity="101" load-factor="0.85">
      <key-constraint>java.lang.String</key-constraint>
      <value-constraint>org.springframework.data.gemfire.repository.sample.User</value-constraint>
      <cache-loader>
        <class-name>org.springframework.data.gemfire.support.SpringContextBootstrappingInitializerIntegrationTest$UserDataStoreCacheLoader</class-name>
      </cache-loader>
    </region-attributes>
  </region>
  <initializer>
    <class-name>org.springframework.data.gemfire.support.SpringContextBootstrappingInitializer</class-name>
    <parameter name="basePackages">
      <string>org.springframework.data.gemfire.support.sample</string>
    </parameter>
  </initializer>
</cache>]]>
		</programlisting>

	</section>

</chapter>
