<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="mapping" version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>POJO mapping</title>

	<section xml:id="mapping.entities">
		<title>Entity Mapping</title>

		<para>
			Spring Data GemFire provides support to map entities that will be stored in a GemFire data grid.
			The mapping metadata is defined using annotations at the domain classes just like this:
		</para>

		<example>
			<title>Mapping a domain class to a GemFire Region</title>

			<programlisting language="java">@Region("People")
public class Person {

  @Id Long id;
  String firstname;
  String lastname;

  @PersistenceConstructor
  public Person(String firstname, String lastname) {
    // …
  }

  …
}
			</programlisting>

		</example>

		<para>
			The first thing you see here is the <interfacename>@Region</interfacename> annotation that can be used to
			customize the Region in which the <classname>Person</classname> class is stored in. The
			<interfacename>@Id</interfacename> annotation can be used to annotate the property that shall be used as
			the Cache key. The <interfacename>@PersistenceConstructor</interfacename> annotation actually helps
			disambiguating multiple potentially available constructors taking parameters and explicitly marking the one
			annotated as the one to be used to create entities. With none or only a single constructor you can omit the
			annotation.
		</para>

		<para>
			In addition to storing entities in top-level Regions, entities can be stored in GemFire Sub-Regions, as so:
		</para>

		<programlisting language="java">@Region("/Users/Admin")
public class Admin extends User {
  …
}

@Region("/Users/Guest")
public class Guest extends User {
  ...
}
		</programlisting>

		<para>
			Be sure to use the full-path of the GemFire Region, as defined in Spring Data GemFire XML namespace
			configuration meta-data, as specified in the <literal>id</literal> or <literal>name</literal> attributes
			of the <literal>&lt;*-region&gt;</literal> bean definition.
		</para>

		<para>
			As alternative to specifying the Region in which the entity will be stored using the
			<interfacename>@Region</interfacename> annotation on the entity class, you can also specify the
			<interfacename>@Region</interfacename> annotation on the entity's <interfacename>Repository</interfacename>
			abstraction. See <xref linkend="gemfire-repositories"/> for more details.
		</para>

		<para>
			However, let's say you want to store a Person in multiple GemFire Regions (e.g. <literal>People</literal>
			and <literal>Customers</literal>), then you can define your corresponding <interfacename>Repository</interfacename>
			interface abstractions like so:
		</para>

		<programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[@Region("People")
public interface PersonRepository extends GemfireRepository<Person, String> {
…
}

@Region("Customers")
public interface CustomerRepository extends GemfireRepository<Person, String> {
...
}
		]]></programlisting>
	</section>

	<section xml:id="mapping.pdx-serializer">
    <title>Mapping PDX Serializer</title>

    <para>Spring Data GemFire provides a custom
    <interfacename>PDXSerializer</interfacename> implementation that uses the
    mapping information to customize entity serialization. Beyond that it
    allows customizing the entity instantiation by using the Spring Data
    <interfacename>EntityInstantiator</interfacename> abstraction. By default
    the serializer uses a <classname>ReflectionEntityInstantiator</classname>
    that will use the persistence constructor of the mapped entity (either the
    single declared one or explicitly annoted with
    <interfacename>@PersistenceConstructor</interfacename>). To provide values
    for constructor parameters it will read fields with name of the
    constructor parameters from the <interfacename>PDXReader</interfacename>
    supplied.</para>

    <example>
      <title>Using @Value on entity constructor parameters</title>

      <programlisting language="java">public class Person {

  public Person(@Value("#root.foo") String firstname, @Value("bean") String lastname) {
    // …
  }

}  </programlisting>

    </example>

    <para>The entity annotated as such will get the field <code>foo</code>
    read from the <interfacename>PDXReader</interfacename> and handed as
    constructor parameter value for <code>firstname</code>. The value for
    <code>lastname</code> will be the Spring bean with name
    <code>bean</code>.</para>
  </section>

</chapter>
